On the 29th of April 1868, the United States
government signed the Treaty of Fort Laramie
with several leaders of the Sioux tribes
of the Great Plains. By November many of
the older leaders of the Sioux like Red
Cloud had agreed to its terms and went to
live on fed-eral-run reservations. One younger
leader was militant in his resistance though.
Eight years later Sitting Bull would win the
most famous Sioux victory over the US. How
did this young member of the Hunkpapa tribe go
from local tribal leader to the victor of the
Battle of the Little Bighorn? This is the story
of Sitting Bull and the Great Sioux War.
The man known to history as Sitting Bull was born
sometime between 1831 and 1837 in Many Caches,
a collection of native American storage pits
located in Dakota. He was born into a noble
family of the Hunkpapa, a sub-tribe of the Lakota
people. The Lakota and the Dakota collectively
made up the Sioux Native Americans that dominated
the region from the western edges of the Great
Lakes around Minnesota all the way through the
Great Plains and the Dakotas to Montana. Sitting
Bull had several names during his life. For
instance, he was known as Ȟoká Psíče, meaning
‘Jumping Badger’ in his childhood years.
Later he acquired the name Tȟatȟáŋka Íyotake,
which translates as ‘Sitting Bull’.
Sitting Bull’s father was also called Sitting
Bull. At the time of his son’s birth, he was chief
of the Hunkpapa tribe along with his two brothers,
Four Horns and Looks-for-Him-in-a-Tent.
Sitting Bull’s mother was Her-Holy-Door.
He had two known sisters, Good Feather and Twin
Woman, as well as one half-brother, Fool Dog, who
lived with his mother’s clan, the Arikaras.
By the age of ten, Jumping Badger was recognised
as an accomplished hunter, having already
killed his first buffalo. Four years later,
the young boy’s martial talents helped him
attain his first battlefield kill against
his people’s most hated rivals, the Crows.
In 1845 the Hunkpapa were engaged in a border
war with the Crows. On the third day the war
party ambushed a band of a dozen Crow riders,
and in the ensuing melee Jumping Badger chased
down a mounted enemy and knocked him off his
horse with a tomahawk. Returning victorious to
their camp, a white eagle feather representing
bravery was placed in his hair to symbolise his
transition to manhood. His body was painted black
from head-to-toe and he was led around the camp
to rapturous applause. Then in the final act
Jumping Badger was renamed Sitting Bull by his
father, who also gifted his son a traditional
buffalo-hide shield he would use for the rest of
his life. Eager to grow his standing as a master
warrior, he took part in numerous successful war
expeditions throughout the 1850s that expanded
Hunkpapa territory. During these skirmishes he
won about a dozen one-on-one battles, all of which
were independently observed and recorded by other
men. Eventually his name struck so much fear that
his comrades would shout “We are Sitting Bull’s
boys” to demoralise the enemy before they had
even started fighting. His insatiable desire for
glory however would come at a price in 1856 when,
challenged by a foe to a one-to-one duel with
muskets, he was shot by a bullet in the foot.
Despite killing his opponent, he would live for
the rest of his life with a limp.
In this period Sitting Bull not only excelled as
a soldier, but also as a mystic. In the same year
of his injury he became a Wicasa Wakan, which
translates as ‘sacred man’ and which according
to Lakota custom was an individual who had the
ability to have dream visions. In order to attain
this spiritual status Sitting Bull’s chest and
back muscles were skewered and he was hung in
the air until he was able to tear them loose
in a ritual known as a sun-dance sacrifice.
The following year, after being recognised as
a man that exemplified the Lakota virtues of
bravery and wisdom, he was made war chief of the
Hunkpapa tribe in a ceremony that took place at
the mouth of the Grand River, near his birthplace.
As part of the tribal rites, Sitting Bull smoked a
pipe made from porcupine quills and duck feathers
and drank a cup containing water and sweetgrass,
before being presented with a cane that symbolised
long life. Sitting Bull’s father was killed around
this time, in 1859, while fighting against the
hated Crows. Having seen his father’s dead corpse,
the furious Sitting Bull chased the culprit
down and killed him to exact revenge.
Sitting Bull’s ascension to leadership coincided
with the rise of the Wasichus, the Lakota term for
the new settlers, who at the end of the 1850s
were emerging as the single biggest threat to
his tribe’s existence. After decades of massive
settlement around the Great Lakes, the influx of
hundreds of thousands of immigrants into the US
from Europe every year was now fuelling American
expansion further westward again towards the Great
Plains in the 1850s and 1860s. More and more of
these settlers began moving in and encroaching on
Lakota lands bringing with them disease, alcohol,
and livestock that ate the prairie grasses where
wild buffalo fed. In March 1856 the power dynamic
between the newcomers and natives was starkly
outlined by General William Harney when he
gathered Lakota tribe leaders to inform them of
a treaty of his own making that had three major
stipulations. The first was that native Americans
who had committed crimes against settlers were to
be handed over to US authorities, the second was
that stolen property must be returned to military
outposts, and the third was that they were not
to loiter near roads used by settlers nor were
they to obstruct any non Native American
travellers. In return the general pledged
that they would enjoy the protection of the US
government, yet this was a treaty in name only.
The US Senate had not ratified it and it had no
legal basis. Most of the Lakota and Dakota people
simply chose to ignore it, leading to a surge in
violent confrontations between the two races in
what are now Minnesota and Iowa, west into the
Dakotas and Nebraska.
Tensions between the various Sioux tribes and
the Euro-American settlers intensified in 1862
when the discovery of gold in the Rocky Mountains
transformed the Missouri River and surrounding
areas into a popular transportation hub for miners
heading westwards, leading to further encroachment
on the lands of the Lakota and Dakota. Within a
very short space of time the Missouri River was
riddled with prospectors, steam-boat captains
and miners. The Dakota War of 1862 marked the
beginning of more intense clashes between the US
government and the various Sioux tribes as huge
numbers of Dakota tribespeople were displaced from
Minnesota and pushed into the Dakota Territory.
Others were rounded up and sent to reservations in
Nebraska. Sitting Bull and his followers had their
power base further west and were only peripherally
involved in the Dakota War, but they would have
been completely aware of the implications of this
westward expansion of the United States. The next
year the invaders signalled their intention to
permanently stay in the area with the construction
of Fort Sully, located a couple of miles above
Fort Pierre on the west bank of the Missouri.
This set the stage for the Battle of Kildeer
Mountain at the end of July 1864, where the gulf
in technology between the two sides was evident
as the US forces used accurate long-range rifles,
cannons, and artillery. By 1865 Sitting Bull’s
attitude towards the settlers was clear among
his compatriots. With the notable exception of
traders who sold guns to his people, he believed
that all other non Native Americans must leave
Lakota territory and never return. Over the next
four years the chief practised what he preached
by leading the offensive against the newcomers.
Others amongst the Lakota, having witnessed the
superiority of the invaders on the battlefield,
favoured a more diplomatic approach and believed
that negotiating with the settlers was the only
realistic survival option. This difference in
opinion caused fractures within the Lakota best
exemplified by Sitting Bull’s multiple raids
on the military stronghold of Fort Rice in
the spring of 1865. As more and more of his
countrymen bent the knee to the invaders,
Sitting Bull stepped up his resistance throughout
1866 and 1867, focusing his military efforts on
another installation called Fort Buford which,
built deep in Lakota territory, represented
the most egregious incursion yet. To the west,
his ally, Red Cloud, harassed the newly-erected
US military forts. Red Cloud, however, would
eventually give in the following year when
he signed a peace deal that put an end to his
guerrilla campaign in the Northern Plains.
Having proven time and time again his
determination to rid his domains of
settlers, and as a highly-respected Lakota
chieftain who was still relatively young,
Sitting Bull was deemed the perfect candidate for
a new position concocted by his uncle, Four Horns,
that broke with tradition. With the plight
of his people only worsening year after year,
Four Horns proposed that his nephew become
the head chief of a Sioux Confederation that
would unite the Lakota and Dakota tribes under one
banner. This coalition of survival came into being
in 1869 when, in the middle of Rosebud Creek,
the Hunkpapas, Blackfeet, Miniconjous, Sans Arcs,
Oglalas, and Cheyennes elected Sitting
Bull as the chief of their confederacy,
a position which gave him authority to make war
and peace. His ascension to this position also
marked a decisive shift away from the aggression
that had characterised much of the 1860s to a
more defensive strategy. Having been the spear of
his people Sitting Bull now became their shield,
withdrawing from direct attacks on forts and
instead prioritising the retention of their
remaining territory. Soon enough they would be
drawn back into conflict though.
Since the Hunkpapas were practitioners
of polygamy, Sitting Bull had many wives
throughout his life including Light Hair,
Snow-on-Her, and Red Woman or Scarlet Woman,
with the latter two becoming bitter rivals.
In 1872 he wed the sisters Four Robes and
Seen-By-Her-Nation. He had six daughters, male
twins, as well as two adopted sons, One Bull and
Jumping Bull. In appearance Sitting Bull was just
under six feet tall and, though he had a solid,
muscular build, he was much more agile than
met the eye. He had striking eyes, a flat nose,
thin lips, and a large head with long dark hair
which, often braided to one side with otter fur,
went down to his shoulders. In personality he
was famously generous, spending later earnings
he got from his celebrity status on lavish feasts
for his friends and kinsmen. Supposedly able to
communicate and talk with them in their song,
he was so fond of birds that one time he even
stopped a feast to fix up a wounded meadowlark. A
nature lover, he was also a man of many talents,
and, aside from being a feared warrior and
respected war chief, was a champion sprinter,
a knowledgeable healer and a revered holy man who
frequently experienced prophetic visions.
As America grew, so did its transport
system, leading to plans for a Northern
Pacific Railway that would cut right through
the heart of the Lakota territory. Swapping
their old powder muskets for superior rifles
with cartridge bullets, indigenous resistance
against the railroad intensified in the early
1870s, with nighttime assaults on encampments
of railroad engineers on the north bank of the
Yellowstone River which cut through the sacred
Elk Valley of the Lakota homeland. According to
Lakota lore, during one battle at Arrow Creek,
Sitting Bull took some tobacco, his pipe, bow, and
rifle, and calmly walked straight into the middle
of the contested, open plains. Then, with enemy
bullets whistling past or hitting the dirt around
him, he sat down, lit his pipe, and exclaimed:
“Who other Indians with to smoke with me come”
upon which four of his compatriots joined
the smoking party. After they had finished
the tobacco bowl and Sitting Bull had cleaned his
pipe, his companions rushed back to safety but the
Sioux chieftain didn’t follow their lead, instead
taking his time to get up and walk serenely back
to friendly lines. Despite his bravery, Sitting
Bull’s war bands inflicted very few casualties
against the better armed and organised railroad
expedition, which they shadowed for a week or
so after the initial fighting at Arrow Creek.
With plans for the railway still in full swing
despite Siting Bull’s opposition, the next year
another survey expedition set off towards the
Yellowstone. Leading the Seventh Cavalry was
Lieutenant Colonel George Armstrong Custer,
who was nicknamed Long Hair for the distinctive
red-gold hair that tumbled down to just above
his shoulders. In early August 1873, from the
time his soldiers were spotted by the Sioux,
Custer pursued a series of inconclusive skirmishes
with the Lakota, a stark contrast to what would
happen during their second meeting years later.
For now though, the natives held their ground
in what would turn out to be their last battle
with the railroad companies and their protection
escorts for some time. In 1873 an economic
crash occurred in the US owing to excessive
speculation on the railways. American and European
economic markets were crippled for several years,
literally stopping the development of the Northern
Pacific Railway in its tracks.
With the pace of non Native American expansion
temporarily slowing down, over the next few years
Sitting Bull intensified his military campaigns
against the Crows who were one of the tribes who,
having accepted the 1868 treaty, had allowed the
settlers to establish a reservation and support
agencies on their territory. Simultaneously
he also repulsed an invasion of around 150
prospectors who had trespassed on his homeland
in February 1874 to look for sources of gold.
By this point Sitting Bull’s consistent hostility
had made it clear that he would never willingly
acquiesce to US rule, fuelling speculation that a
bigger, more devastating war was inevitable. The
Great Sioux War of 1876 kicked off when Sitting
Bull refused to sell a sacred piece of his domain
called the Black Hills to the US government, who
wanted to mine it for gold. On the 17th of March
1876 in snowy and icy conditions, American troops
launched a surprise attack against the Northern
Cheyenne tribe on the Powder River in the Montana
Territory, during which they burned down half
of their camp, leaving them without shelter and
provisions and forcing them to find refuge with
Sitting Bull, who offered it generously. With
the enemy closing in, Sitting Bull appealed to
the spiritual world to guide him and in June,
after completing sacred rites over four days he
was suddenly struck by a profound vision of the
invaders turned upside down. To Sitting Bull and
those who deciphered it, this was a portent
of a great victory to come very soon.
On the 17th of May 1876, Lieutenant Colonel Custer
had led a column of 750 men out of Fort Abraham
Lincoln with the intention of destroying Sitting
Bull’s forces for good. Aided by Crow scouts,
the plan was for Custer to march up the Rosebud
River to Sitting Bull’s village and attack it.
After overpowering them, the Sioux were expected
to flee north where a force overseen by generals
Alfred Terry and John Gibbon would block their
path and finish them off. By the 24th of June,
Custer knew that his force had already been
spotted by Lakota scouts who had been observing
them from a distance. Fearing that the warriors
in the village he intended to take would scatter
out in all directions, he then made the fateful
decision to attack on the afternoon of the 25th,
rather than waiting until the morning of the
26th. In doing so, Custer was essentially going
in blind because the size of Sitting Bull’s
war party was unknown. Then, on the afternoon
of the 25th of June, as the Lakota hurriedly
painted themselves and readied their weapons,
Custer made another tactical blunder when he
divided his regiment into three separate groups,
meaning each was isolated from the rest.
Custer’s cavalry, led by Major Marcus Reno,
were the first to charge down into the southern
end of the village. As they let off their first
volleys of bullets, Sitting Bull hurriedly donned
his war gear while his stepson, One Bull, handed
him a Winchester repeating rifle and a six-shooter
pistol. As the horsemen approached the first
Hunkpapa tipis just before a river-bend, some
of them dismounted, forming a thin static line
of fire. After advancing about a hundred yards
they dropped to their bellies on open ground.
But the return fire was so intense that the
soldiers were forced to retreat into the cover
of a thicket of forest to the right. With the
momentum shifting in the Hunkpapa’s favour, a
squadron of mounted horsemen led by Sitting Bull’s
staunch ally, Crazy Horse, swarmed the enemy
position from all directions forcing them to fall
back to a clearing in the woods. Their unity lost,
isolated pockets of Custer’s soldiers hid
and fired from behind bushes. In utter panic,
the American troopers who weren’t being cut down
by tomahawks and rifles either fled on horses
across the south-east plain or were washed away by
the strong river current along with their steeds.
100 or so survivors out of 175 scrabbled to a
high point to the east of the river as their
wounded comrades were killed below.
As this was happening, Custer and his division
were approaching the village from the north.
He stationed his three regiments of 210 men
in the upper part of Medicine Tail. Expecting
to see his commander Frederick Benteen arrive,
he was instead met by the horde of Sioux warriors
who had made their way north. For a short time,
Custer’s men held off the encroaching warriors,
then one massive native charge panicked the horses
into a great stampede. Galloping in the direction
of the river, they were caught by Cheyenne women
who emptied their saddlebags of ammunition
and tossed them to the attacking warriors.
The panicked columns split into two, with those
in the south cut down individually or in groups
while the other stragglers, including Custer,
scrambled to a hilltop at the end of a ridge
to make their last stand. There he and his
men met their demise in a flurry of dust,
smoke and hand-to-hand fighting, with the
last of them finished off by a final assault.
The other regiments led by Reno and Benteen were
the last to be defeated at dawn on the 26th of
June. Broken and demoralised, Sitting Bull allowed
them to retreat. In total nearly half of Custer’s
700-strong regiment had been killed or wounded,
in what had been without doubt the greatest
military triumph in their history and an emphatic
fulfilment of Sitting Bull’s dream vision. Sitting
Bull had spent most of the battle observing and
tending to the wounded, a not unusual thing for
a leader in his forties who was beyond the
peak of his fighting abilities.
Following this victory, the Sioux confederacy
was at the pinnacle of its powers, but they
had also spelled their own destruction as the
horrified American public demanded vengeance. In
the aftermath of Little Bighorn, several small
and mostly inconclusive battles were fought
between the Sioux and the Americans in and around
Yellowstone. The increased presence of government
soldiers and the planned construction of permanent
forts in the middle of hunting ranges was designed
to starve the Native Americans out by disrupting
their main food supply, the buffalo herds.
This proved so effective and demoralising that
the Sioux Confederacy began to break apart,
with the Sans Arc and Miniconjou chiefs the
first major groups to defect from the alliance,
giving up their freedom in exchange for life on
government-run reservations. During the freezing
winter of 1876 to 1877, after being identified
by the US media as the evil savage responsible
for Custer’s fall, the American military attempted
to hunt down Sitting Bull and his shrinking circle
of allies. The Sioux were chased from camp to
camp, their supplies and shelters set aflame. In
May 1877, after a traumatic winter, he and his
men crossed the northern frontier into Canada
to seek refuge. Sitting Bull quickly became
acquainted with the North-West Mounted Police,
who accepted their presence on the condition that
they respect their laws, one of which would strip
away their right to asylum if they went over
the frontier and back into the USA. At first
assured by the Canadians they would protect
them from any cross-border American attack,
the decision to come to a territory known as
the Grandmother seemed like a wise one. Yet
while the elders of the Sioux were willing to
follow Canadian law, hot-blooded youngsters of
their clan disregarded it, continuing hostilities
with other tribes or American troops and hunting
buffalo on the other side of the border. Thus,
soon enough, diplomatic tensions between the US
and the Canadians escalated over the fugitives
and a big diplomatic row erupted. Still, during
a meeting with American envoys sent to urge them
to surrender, on the 16th of October 1877, Sitting
Bull made it clear that he would not return to
the US under any conditions.
Sitting Bull and his men now attempted to settle
more permanently in the Prairies of Canada,
busying themselves with hunting innumerable
buffalo herds that roamed freely north of the
border. In the spring of 1878, his ranks were
swelled with the addition of more refugees, the
total number of indigenous immigrants increasing
to roughly 6,500 people. With so many more mouths
to feed the once flourishing buffalo herds,
which also fed the indigenous Canadian tribes,
began to reduce in size dramatically, creating
tensions between the newcomers and the natives
here north of the border. In response, Sitting
Bull and his men began raiding south of the
border again. During one of these illegal,
southward migrations, on the 17th of July 1879,
Sitting Bull and 600 of his followers were caught
by surprise by an American force led by General
Nelson Miles. During the Battle of Milk River,
as both parties took potshots at each other,
a senior Crow commander called Magpie,
who was allied with the US contingent,
rode out and challenged Sitting Bull to single
combat, which he accepted. Riding their horses
towards each other with rifles cocked, Magpie’s
weapon jammed and misfired and an instant later
the crown of his head was blown off by a deadeye
shot from Sitting Bull, who cut off what was left
of his scalp to claim triumph.
In the summer of 1880, relations between the Sioux
and the Canadian authorities deteriorated further,
as the frequent cross-border raids by the Lakotas
and others continued. The Canadian provincial
authorities had entered into clandestine talks
with the Americans with the goal of transferring
Sitting Bull and his followers back south of the
border. By early 1881, while he and a group of
hardcore loyalists sat hungrily at their village
on the frontier just near the Wood Mountain
police post, the majority of Sitting Bull’s
people had already deserted him to go to live on
the Indian reservation at Fort Buford. Finally,
on the 12th of July 1881, Sitting Bull made
the agonising decision to forfeit his freedom
after being convinced to do so by a trader by
the name of Jean Louis Legaré who had become
friendly with the Lakota during their four-year
long Canadian exile. Eight days later, tired,
hungry and with rotting clothes, Sitting Bull and
nearly 200 followers entered the courtyard of Fort
Buford. To mark the start of his imprisonment
the defeated rebel handed over his weapon to
the commanding officer and poignantly remarked: “I
wish it to be remembered that I was the last man
of my tribe to surrender my rifle.”
Having handed himself in, Sitting Bull was
promised by Major David Brotherton he would
spend the rest of his days at the Standing
Rock Agency where most of his brethren
who had already surrendered were living,
but the higher-ups were soon starting
to reconsider. Worried that the defeated
renegade could potentially become the centre of
renewed rebellion, he and his entourage were to
be delivered further up the Missouri River to Fort
Randall. Informed in September 1881 of the change,
Sitting Bull flew into a wild rage as his captors
had once again broken their promise. Nonetheless,
he and his group of followers were ushered on
board a steamer called the Sherman bound for Fort
Randall where he spent twenty miserable months.
Seeing that the ageing commander posed little
further threat to the government by then, several
army officers appealed to the Secretary of War,
Robert Lincoln, requesting to transfer them back
to Standing Rock. The petition worked and by the
end of April 1883 the captives were being boated
back down the Missouri River to Fort Yates and
the Standing Rock Agency. Disembarking
in May 1883 to Fort Yates, Sitting Bull,
who had begun to begrudgingly accept that the
old ways of his ancestors were dead, resolved
to tow a middle line between preserving them and
adapting to the new life imposed on him. He would
learn how to sow and harvest the land like his
jailers and he would even enrol his children in
their education systems. At the same he would
still try to act as the Hunkpapa chief of old,
protecting his people from the injustices of the
new order. In this regard, his main nemesis over
the coming years would be the overseer of Standing
Rock, James McLaughlin, a man who imposed order
by keeping his subjects divided into squabbling
factions and by using the coercive power of ration
control to achieve his aims. In an indication of
the dynamic that would define their relationship,
Sitting Bull told the agent upon his arrival
that, since he had no experience of doing it,
he would not be planting seeds this year
and that instead, he would look around
to see how it was done before he tried it out.
MacLaughlin remarked that the chief was “pompous,
vain, and boastful” and a man “of very mediocre
ability, rather dull, and much the inferior of
his other lieutenants in intelligence.”
In the spring of 1884 Sitting Bull settled
on a spot south of the river on the reservation,
extremely close to where he had been born about 50
years earlier. This would be his final residence.
Serious about adapting to the lifestyle of the new
world, over the next couple of years his estate
swelled to 20 horses, 45 cattle, 80 chickens,
and fields full of oats, corn, and potatoes.
Sitting Bull had transformed easily enough from
chief to farmer, while his adopted son, One Bull,
had even swapped the warrior lifestyle for a job
in the local police force. In the meantime any
pretensions to power that Sitting Bull still had
would be ended when, emphasising the importance
of his position as chief in front of a government
committee called the Dawes Committee, one of
America’s most esteemed senators, John A. Logan,
gave him the most brutal dressing down of his
life when he replied: “You were not appointed by
the Great Spirit. Appointments are not made that
way. You have no following, no power, no control,
and no right to any control. If it were not for
the government, you would be freezing and starving
today in the mountains.” Yet, while his formal
rights of chief may have all but disintegrated,
Sitting Bull still had the power of his newfound
celebrity to fall back on. Despite the predicament
he found himself in, the former vanquisher of
Custer became a subject of fascination for the
American public in his later years. He embarked
on a nationwide tour with the Buffalo Bill
theatre troupe headed by the showman Bill Cody
during which, fully clad in traditional garb,
he smoked a pipe and cooked food while a presenter
delivered a lecture on the inner workings of the
Native Americans. He made a handsome amount
of money through his participations in one of
the world’s most famous entertainment troupes
in the late nineteenth century. Eventually,
though, Sitting Bull’s time in the limelight
was cut short and he was prevented from
going out on tour again in 1886.
After this, Sitting Bull led a quiet and
peaceful life at his homestead by the Grand River,
even sending a tomahawk to former Secretary of
the Interior Samuel J. Kirkwood as a gesture of
appreciation. That was until the passing of the
General Allotment Act of 1887 compelled him to
intervene on behalf of the Lakota once again. A
law so horrific it even led to the reconciliation
of the Hunkpapa with their old rivals, the Crows,
the idea was that every native family was to
receive 160 acres or less of land in return
for US citizenship. Once every indigenous family
had received their small parcel, any land that was
left was to be bought at a cut-price 50 cents an
acre to encourage non Native American settlement.
The once boundless Sioux lands, reduced to the
size of a reservation, were to be subdivided
into even smaller reservations. Although the
scheme was rejected by most of the Sioux,
through intimidation and manipulation the
government coerced three-quarters of the natives
to accept the agreement by 1890. Thus, with the
last vestiges of their old life crumbling around
them Native Americans turned to spirituality as
a bastion of opposition. Beginning in March 1890,
an indigenous holy man and self-proclaimed
messiah named Wovoka, claimed that by performing
something called a Ghost Dance his people could be
transported to a perfect, pre-contact paradise of
peace, buffalo and untouched wilderness that
represented the world before the destructive
arrival of the Europeans. Inspired by this, in
mid-1890, after a particularly poor harvest,
the Ghost Dance movement erupted across the
Standing Rock Reservation. Most worryingly for
the men overseeing the land allotment, prophets
of the movement claimed that the Ghost Dance would
even protect its acolytes from bullets. Sitting
Bull did not do anything to halt its spread,
as his people abandoned their cabins, set up
their tipis and engaged in the Ghost Dance.
He perhaps viewed this as an opportunity
to revitalise the power and influence that
had been stripped away from him years earlier,
but equally, from McLaughlin’s viewpoint, this
was a chance to finally take Sitting Bull down by
painting him as the high priest of a destabilising
religious movement that was threatening the
newfound peace of the Great Plains.
As the ghost dances assumed a more violent
undertone, President Benjamin Harrison ordered
his Secretary of War to contain it if it got out
of hand, resulting in the arrival of troops to the
region on the 20th of November 1890 at the Pine
Ridge and Rosebud agencies near the Standing Rock
reservation. As ominous clouds gathered, Sitting
Bull was reminded of a vision that had come to him
soon after his transfer to Standing Rock from
Fort Randall in which a meadowlark had warned
him that his own people, the Lakotas, would be the
ones that killed him. On the 27th of November, as
people wildly flailed their bodies to and fro in
a dance circle on the Hunkpapa chief’s property,
Sitting Bull was visited by a Hunkpapa policeman
and one of McLaughlin’s favourites, Lone Man,
who on behalf of the reservation boss urged him to
tell his followers to stop with the ghost dances.
Sitting Bull replied that their ceremony harmed no
one, and that if the settlers had their religion
his followers should be able to practice theirs
too in peace. By this time McLaughlin had already
decided that, when the weather turned colder, he
was going to get his Lakota police to arrest their
former leader, however the US military soon took
over the case. A Lakota policeman by the name of
Bull Head who had fought at Little Bighorn, was
tasked with spying on Sitting Bull after rumours
emerged that he wanted to leave the Standing
Rock Agency to meet up with other ghost dancers
at nearby Pine Ridge. Planting two spies into the
tribal council, they reported that Sitting Bull
did in fact want to do this and that his followers
would shoot any policeman who tried to obstruct
their passage. Thus, on the 15th of December
1890, at 6am, a squadron of Lakota policemen
led by Bull Head burst into his cabin, wrestled
him to the ground, and walked him outside, but the
noise they had created had alerted Sitting Bull’s
entire settlement. Furious crowds implored them to
release him and surrounded the policemen as Bull
Head and another led their culprit to a police
wagon, and then suddenly the sound of a Winchester
rifle rang through the air. Bull Head’s long-term
rival, Catch-the-Bear, had shot him. As the Lakota
policemen fell to the ground he aimed his revolver
upwards and fired off his own shot at Sitting
Bull. The chief caught the bullet in his chest,
and then an instant later he was killed by
a shot to the head by Bull Head’s underling,
Red Tomahawk. A point-blank firefight broke
out claiming the lives of Sitting Bull’s sons,
Jumping Bull and 17 year-old Crow Foot, and
grandson Chase-Them-Wounded, as well as five
policemen. Sitting Bull was probably nearing
sixty years of age at the time of his death.
Born into indigenous royalty, Sitting Bull was
one of the last generations to enjoy a typical
native American childhood out on the Great Plains
amongst the buffalo herds. From an early age,
he displayed the qualities of a great leader,
earning a reputation not only for courage and
martial prowess, but also for generosity, humility
and spirituality. Proving his worth as a hardened
warrior and skilled tactician in multiple battles,
he was appointed chief of the Hunkpapa tribe in
the 1850s as the threat of settler expansion
picked up speed. Over the next decade or so,
he dedicated himself to preserving the
independence of his people and fought valiantly
to defend the lands of the Hunkpapa from westward
US expansion. In the late 1860s this indomitable
spirit of resistance, unmatched among his peers,
was recognised when he was made head chief of the
Sioux Confederation. By this point having seen
enough action to know that his enemy’s weapons
and tactics were superior to his own, he decided
to switch to a more defensive posture. After
repelling an incursion by railway companies
looking to lay track down in his territory,
Sitting Bull illustrated to the American
government that he would never surrender.
During the Great Sioux War of 1876 his astonishing
victory over General George Custer at the Battle
of Little Bighorn made him the most prominent
and feared rebel in the United States. But it
was a short-lived victory. It ultimately led to an
American offensive so devastating that the Sioux
Confederacy was broken up and Sitting Bull and his
hungry band had no choice but to flee to Canada
for four years. Eventually the disappearance
of buffalo there and rising diplomatic tensions
between Canada and the United States, compelled
Sitting Bull and what remained of his followers
to join their brothers and sisters at Standing
Rock Agency. There he tried to act as a shield
of his people while also adapting to modern
American life. While flourishing as a farmer
and taking advantage of his famous name to make
money on various nationwide tours, deep down
Sitting Bull was a lost soul yearning for the days
of old. The arrival of the Ghost Dance movement,
with its emphasis on a pre-contact utopia,
filled him with purpose once more but it also
spelled his downfall. Viewing it as a threat
to the established order, the military tasked
Lakota policemen with apprehending him. The
tragedy was that the greatest of the Sioux
chiefs died fighting his own people.
What do you think of Sitting Bull? Was he the
last great native American chief who bravely
resisted US government encroachments on the
lands of tribes like the Hunkpapa, or was
his cause doomed from the beginning? Please
let us know in the comment section and in the
meantime thank you very much for watching.